Dita ROMs is one of the most influential
designers to ever live even if you don't
know who he is you probably use the
products that were inspired by his
thinking every single day he crafted the
10 principles for good design which are
kind of like the design Bible but I
can't help but wonder is our blind
commitment to these principles holding
us back from designing a better future
for example this iPhone it's Sleek it's
simple it's supposedly a product of Dita
ROMs less but better design philosophy
but throughout this video you'll see
that less is not always better and the
Mantra is rooted in 20th century
thinking it's not the answer to the
sustainable design problems we're facing
today we'll go even deeper though Beyond
ROMs celebrated 10 principles there is a
key ingredient that was revolutionary
for his time but no one seems to talk
about now before you all take out your
pitchforks and torches convinced that
I'm desecrating the design Bible it's
important to note that ROMs himself
never wanted these principles to be
permanent they were always meant to be
updated so let's get to it so the first
principle I want to talk about is good
design is honest on the surface this
seems like a great principle I mean who
can argue with honesty but I think this
runs counter to what a designer
fundamentally does on many levels if we
use dieter's definition of honesty I
could make a very strong argument that
good designers are about as honest as
used car salesmen hot dog a sale in fact
we're probably even worse because at
least with a used car salesman you know
exactly what to expect with designers
their influence is so subtle that it
often goes by undetected honesty is just
not the first word I'd use when
describing good design so take this pair
of sunglasses as an example it covers
half your face and the right pair that's
designed well can accentuate your
attractive features while downplaying
your less flattering ones a big part of
design is about focusing people's
attention on positive things and away
from negative things it's like an
Instagram filter but for products data
romp's principle of honest design
probably has its roots in the Bauhaus
concept of Truth to materials
essentially truth to materials promotes
authenticity arguing that you should
never make one material look like
another but my question is why not
keeping up with the eyewear theme let's
look at the glasses frames that Dita
ROMs is wearing they're probably made
from cellulose acetate acetate is meant
to mimic the coloration you'd see on
tortoise shell frames from the early
20th century the only way to get this
material honestly is to kill a hawksbill
turtle which is a critically endangered
species and then turn its shell into a
pair of eyewear frames but it's been
illegal to use tortoise shell as a
material and product since like 1977. so
our Dita ROMs glasses dishonest because
they're trying to make cellulose acetate
look like tortoise shell I mean I guess
under the Bauhaus definition yeah but I
don't have a problem with it and Dieter
doesn't seem to either hundreds of
thousands of fake tortoise Shelf frames
are made from cellulose acetate every
single year it's a beautiful pattern and
if you try to harvest it the honest way
you'd have to hunt and kill Turtles to
the point of Extinction it's the same
thing with any design even mundane
things like this external hard drive
it's designed to appear thinner than it
actually is by breaking up the surfaces
into different materials and textures is
that dishonest I mean I don't think so a
big part of design is about elevating
the perceived value of a product take a
look at this 50 calculator designed by
ROMs and his team everything is
harmoniously spaced the glossy
dome-shaped buttons reflect light like
little shiny jelly beans the Strategic
color accents make the most important
buttons pop everything about this design
just screams balance precision and
Clarity and that's the exact emotional
response you want to have when you look
at a calculator it's a tool for precise
calculation and that's why this
calculator retails for fifty dollars but
this Staples calculator is four dollars
I mean sure the brown calculator is
probably functionally better because of
its good design it's probably made a
little bit better but it's not 10 times
better you're paying 10 times more for
the emotional response that this object
creates in you this isn't just a
calculator anymore either it's a symbol
of Purity and Order plus the brown
calculator is a design icon which is
also totally emotional and sentimental
none of that value is grounded in any
kind of objective truth it's still just
a plastic calculator so is it the design
dishonest and how it creates a meaning
beyond the sum of its parts or is it
dishonest with how expensive it is I
would say no but according to the way
that Dieter wrote this principle you
would think yes but here's the thing
dishonest or not it's still a great
design as long as people value things
Beyond just their functional utility
this will always be the case that's why
I don't agree with the idea of good
design being honest at least as far as
ROMs defines it if some of this sounds
familiar I actually made a video on this
topic last year that was going viral but
a copyright claim brought it down I do
have many new insights on this topic
though so keep watching if you could
click the like button to help me out
with the YouTube algorithm I'd really
really appreciate it so that I can get
get this video back to where it was it
makes a really big difference in
spreading this important message to
Young designers but anyway I haven't
even gotten into the act of actually
selling your ideas in a corporate
setting as a designer there's an old
saying in the design world that paper
lies like hell designers use all sorts
of visual trickery like beautiful
sketches and renders to sell their ideas
a great designer is a great salesman
it's just that designers convince you
with pictures and prototypes whereas
traditional salesmen convince you with
words if you walk into any design studio
and look at any of the concepts pinned
up on the wall you'll naturally
gravitate towards the ideas that are
drawn or rendered the best you can hide
all sorts of design flaws with a
well-presented concept sketch you can
distort the proportions you can use
flattering Lighting in your renders or
place your physical prototype on a
pedestal to make it seem more valuable I
just find the good design is honest
principle to not really be in line with
my experience or looking for captivating
and emotional stories imbued in our
products we don't always want honesty
sometimes we want enchantment before we
get into the next section I want to talk
about shaper 3D imagine the convenience
of Post-it notes and the sophistication
of 3D CAD coming together in one
software package that shaper 3D plus you
can use it on your iPad this comes in
super handy when you're on the go and
inspiration strikes or you're in the
middle of a client meeting and want to
sketch up a quick High Fidelity concept
if you're just starting to learn the
basics of Cad and 3D printing this is an
amazing tool that has a far more
accessible and intuitive user interface
than any other 3D modeling tool that
I've used using a stylus to draw is
really where shaper 3D stands out plus
it's a lot more affordable than other
more expensive software CAD packages
it's just a great mobile tool for
creating and showing 3D models on the go
whether you're designing something as
simple as a workbench or as complex as
an engagement ring shaper 3D has you
covered it's a great tool for engineers
designers Architects 3D printing
hobbyists and even students or recent
design grads go click the link in the
description to get 10 off shaper 3D with
a code design Theory 10. back to the
video the next principle is good design
is as little design as possible the
classic less but better Mantra is the
crowning Jewel of ROM's principles but
it's probably one of the most commonly
misinterpreted ones first of all it's
led to an entire generation of designers
losing their minds every time they see a
rounded rectangle
oh
I mean sure this is great design work
but why does it look like they were all
designed by Dieter ROMs in 1959 if you
really respect Dieter ROMs as a designer
you would Forge your own path just like
he did secondly many designers took this
principle to mean let's just strip
everything down to the bone we often see
a surface level application of his
principles resulting in products that
may appear simple but are anything but
simple in terms of functionality cost or
usability getting rid of essential
usability features might make things
visually simpler but it often
complicates the object's function when a
product loses too many of its controls
the remaining ones are left to pick up
the slack so you have two buttons that
do like 10 things holding down tapping
performing a finger ritual dance you've
traded intuitive interaction for a
device that needs an instruction manual
or chairs that are too uncomfortable to
actually sit in for more than 10 minutes
or computers that are missing headphone
jacks or functional ports the true
purpose of minimalism was to ease user
experience by limiting options but
instead it's mostly used as an aesthetic
statement so you end up with visual
Simplicity that's a functional nightmare
it's like telling someone to clean their
room by shoving everything under the bed
complex design doesn't always over
complicate it clarifies less isn't
always more sometimes it's just less
there's also the ironic Twist of
manufacturing processes as it relates to
minimalist products the mission of the
Bauhaus movement and the same spirit
that data ROM subscribed to was all
about making good products that were
accessible to everyone but then you've
got Apple using manufacturing techniques
that are exorbitantly intricate and
expensive the result is a design that's
visually minimalist but financially Out
Of Reach for most people in their
pursuit of as little design as possible
they've ironically created products for
as few people as possible and then
you've got Johnny ive's 65 000 turntable
it's a blatant symbol of desire and
opulent statement piece but that was
never the point of the Bauhaus or
minimalist movements they're aimed to
create simple useful designs that are
accessible to everyone one it was Beauty
born out of purpose and uncompromised by
mass production but somehow we've worked
this ideology focusing on The
Superficial aesthetic while neglecting
the core principles now I want to be
very clear here the problem here isn't
about minimalist design or even the
existence of luxury products there's not
even an inherent issue with merging
these two elements I've done it before
too the real problem here is with the
unquestioning idolization of Dita ROMs
and its principles while not
understanding their true meaning there
is sometimes a more practical reason why
minimalist design is so expensive though
and it's not just because it's what's in
style it's also because execution for
good minimalist design has to be perfect
it's the difference between simple and
elegant versus boring and basic fewer
elements means that every detail is
under a spotlight so ensuring these
details are perfect can drive up
production costs in this way the pursuit
of minimalism can ironically lead to
exclusivity rather than the intended
goal of universal accessibility a
customer would never know notice these
little specific details but it's a major
reason why Apple products just
subconsciously feel premium and Amazon
Basics products feel kind of ordinary
ironically you can make an argument that
Amazon Basics is more in line with data
ROMs less but better philosophy than
Apple is this extends even to color
which is slowly disappearing from our
world because of a push for More
understated Design now we're stuck with
a bunch of lifeless boring gray objects
surrounding us everywhere we go there's
nothing wrong with minimalist design
it's just that it's not appropriate for
every single product so a lot of people
have misinterpreted ROM's principle of
as little design as possible that's not
his fault however I do still think that
the Merit of the principle itself needs
to be critiqued a little bit take a look
at this computer mouse it's a classic
example of Aesthetics overusability and
it's a problem I mean sure this Mouse
looks really nice but I had to use this
mouse in high school and I can't even
begin to describe how uncomfortable it
was to hold Dina ROM says that he hates
when beautification is the priority for
design and I agree with him in many any
cases like with this computer mouse but
I think that a lot of times this as
little design as possible idea is used
as an excuse to make emotionless design
that's cold and oversimplified and not
in line with what the customer needs
datarom sometimes criticizes the
automotive industry for being overly
focused on speed and emotion rather than
functionality he says that he hates the
idea of aesthetic styling and decoration
I Hate Everything what is driven by
fashion especially the cars
they change the styling things every two
years Dieter wants people to be logical
rational actors but nobody makes
decisions that way not even him I mean
the guy drives a Porsche not exactly the
most sensible choice for a car you can't
just ignore the fact that people have
visceral emotional responses to certain
products I've watched hours of Dieter
ROMs footage when researching this video
ROMs always seems happiest when he's
talking about or driving his favorite
cars I know that might not seem like
much here but trust me he's a really
serious guy he does not smile a lot cars
are an emotional purchase most of them
do not use as little design as possible
they're usually much more expressive and
ROM's Porsche is definitely no exception
by the way I'm not criticizing ROMs for
driving a nice car I think it's great
I'm merely using it to point out that
not all products should use as little
design as possible usability is tied to
Aesthetics The Styling of a product
matters if nothing else my design
experience has taught me this even the
most logical design without emotional
resonance will fall flat Form and
Function are one and the same a product
appearance guides our interaction with
it and sometimes you need a little bit
of the embellishment or Flair another
thing to consider is the value of
decorative Beauty purely for beauty's
sake think about what a massive social
and economic benefit it is to have
beautiful architecture that's adorned
with exuberant decorative cultural
elements pretty much every new city
skyline today looks the same I know that
Dieter never intended for this but this
is the Dark Side of minimalism we
express who we are and what we value
through the products we use all of these
designs have so much personality and
cultural heritage and I think that's a
beautiful thing that should be
celebrated not ignored on the bright
side gen Z is pushing more towards
maximalism in design faced with dull
interiors and a world filled with
negativity it seems like they're opting
for this hyper-maximalist vibrantly
colored aesthetic as a counter-reaction
plus with the Advent of artificial
intelligence tools it's simpler than
ever to achieve a maximalist aesthetic
and this is slowly making its way from
images online to fashion and finally
into physical product design obviously
whether it's minimalism maximalism or
anything in between it needs to be done
with a deeper sense of purpose and
meaning here's how I might revise this
principle good design communicates what
is necessary it's just an idea maybe
it's a little bit vague but feel free to
leave a comment and we can talk about
what you might replace this principle
with and on that note feel free to
subscribe or don't but you should you
should subscribe I don't know just
subscribe so now next principle is good
design is environmentally friendly no
one wants to design products that are
environmentally unfriendly at least it's
not on purpose the whole idea of less
but better from an environmental
perspective seems logical but this is
actually a very Antiquated 20th century
line of thinking let's use
fuel-efficient cars as an example I mean
sure it's more efficient and doing more
with less but it's still burning fossil
fuels or slowing down the harm but the
system itself is still harmful this is
the classic less but better strategy
also known as Eco efficiency it's like
applying a Band-Aid to a blister caused
by poorly fitting shoes sure the
Band-Aid might help the pain for a
little while but the real problem is
with the poorly fitting shoes in the
same way Eco efficiency is the Band-Aid
that fails to tackle the root cause our
Reliance on unsustainable resources but
there are ways to actually create
positive impact it's called
eco-effectiveness a term from the book
cradle to cradle it's not about doing
less harm it's about doing more good
some companies are growing packaging
materials and other products using
mushrooms and natural substances instead
of focusing on making less harmful
products they're making products that
can be composted at the end of their
life cycle enriching the soil basically
less but better Eco efficiency is about
doing less harm whereas Eco
Effectiveness is about doing more good
it's about regenerative processes now I
know that Dita ROMs understands the
environmental issues that we face today
we have serious infrastructure and
transportation problems it's also far
easier said than done to completely
change an existing corporate and social
infrastructure but the main point is
that less but better is only treating
the symptoms rather than the core
disease itself which is Humanity's blind
quest for ruthless growth at all costs
let's get into good design is long
lasting I generally agree with Dieter
sentiments on this one but like I said
before if a system is regenerative and
not actually harmful to the environment
it's okay if it's disposable regarding
the fashion comment there is a
legitimate human need for
self-expression through fashion that
will probably never go away these shells
were reshaped and used as jewelry and
they're about 150 000 years old
self-expression in fashion is a deeply
ingrained human need that's probably
been around for as long as we have now I
do think that we consume too much you
don't need to buy a new phone every year
disposable fast fashion is horrible but
doing away with something as integral as
self-expression through the things that
we use and wear is never going to happen
ultimately people are going to buy what
they want to buy it's the designer's job
to help them do it more responsibly a
potential amendment to this could be
something like good design is
regenerative next up is good design is
thorough down to the Last Detail ROM
specifically says that nothing should be
arbitrary or left to chance but I
actually think that arbitrary chance is
a big part of any creative process in
this clip Dita ROMs is pruning the trees
around his garden he Likens the
gardening process to design which is a
beautiful metaphor gardening is organic
and messy and imperfect like tending to
a bonsai tree you can nurture it situate
it in good sunlight prune it but you
can't control every Leaf's shape or each
Branch's exact trajectory you can't
force it to your will you have to let it
flow naturally and design mirrors this
process it's a collaborative effort
where each person on the team brings
their own perspective to the project the
best thing you can do is guide the
process in the right direction and trust
that the other people you're working
with have the end user's best interest
at heart you can't really control it
sometimes technology makes it impossible
to be too thorough anyway especially
with generative design tools you write
software algorithms that can often have
a life of their own same thing with a
lot of modern AI tools Dita ROMs could
not have possibly anticipated this when
he wrote These principles but that's
exactly why they need updating but even
without advanced tech there are also so
many instances where I'm sketching
something and accidentally draw a line
in the wrong spot and then I realize oh
wait a minute that actually might work
better than what I originally had in
mind a lot of times these happy
accidents end up becoming the final
product good design is unobtrusive I
have actually agree with Dieter in
regards to most tools tools usually
should act as an extension of the user's
body they shouldn't get in the way but
the thing is that most products are not
strictly tools I can think of dozens of
successful products that are very
obtrusive and very decorative the PS5 is
one immediately that comes to mind the
design really stands out and is very
imposing I know lots of you will
disagree with me but I would still
consider it an appropriate design for
its use case high heeled shoes are
another great example of a very
obtrusive design that people still
choose to wear that's also why there are
so many different styles of shoes people
want to express themselves in different
ways now I'm betting you Dieter would
say that these examples aren't good
design they're just stylistic fashion
but like I said earlier in the video if
you care about usability you care about
styling and the way that a product makes
someone feel that directly impacts its
function let's move on to good design
makes a product understandable I think
this is probably one of his best
principles but even still I can think of
several counterpoints take these watches
is by Nuka for example they're not
really the most understandable way to
read time but the novel experience of
learning how to read the watch is fun
you feel a sense of accomplishment as
you master the tool over time you
especially see this with luxury watches
that have all sorts of weird dials and
extra features not everything needs to
be about Effectiveness it's why we go
fishing with a fishing rod rather than
just electrocuting everything in the
pond it's like learning a musical
instrument lots of things are
specifically designed with a learning
curve in mind because half the fun comes
from navigating learning and mastering
the product over time next we have good
design makes a product useful you can't
really argue that good design makes a
product useful but you can definitely
argue about what useful means the juicy
Salif is one of the most obvious
examples of this it's supposed to be a
juicer but it's pretty much completely
useless for that purpose you might say
that its use is not to be a juicer at
all but instead its purpose is to strike
up conversation it fulfills a more
abstract need of being a provocative
object it also fulfills the need of
bringing conversation missions around
design and usefulness into a more
mainstream context or if we look at the
Lamborghini Countach most would say it's
a great design if you're interested in
going fast or maybe to inspire the next
generation of sports cars but if you're
a soccer mom who needs to transport her
kids and all of their gear to and from
school it's not a useful design at all I
don't think that this is a bad principle
because who doesn't want useful products
but once again useful could mean a lot
of different things to different people
next up is good design is innovative
I'll keep this one short it's true most
of the time however I don't think that
all good design must be Innovative many
of dieter's designs for brown haven't
changed that much over the last several
decades and they're still just as good
as ever last but not least good design
is aesthetic this one's fine although
maybe a little bit vague since my idea
of aesthetic and dieter's idea are
clearly very different overall I think
the Dita ROMs principles are great as a
starting point they're excellent guiding
principles if you're a young person just
starting out in design ROMs actually
created these principles for a student
students when he first started teaching
they were never meant to be these
immutable truths another problem is that
you can't make a prescriptive set of
principles for all of the design
industry every part of the industry is
just so radically different Dieter wrote
These while working for a German
electrical appliances company in the mid
20th century the principles fit
perfectly for that use case but they
don't really apply to a lot of other
situations it's kind of like how you
hear those vague platitudes you see
people writing about on LinkedIn or
whatever when creating a guiding set of
principles some of the most important
things are making sure that they're
simple understandable and concrete I
think that dieter's principles are
simple and understandable but they're
not very concrete because of how broad
they are at the beginning of the video I
mentioned that data ROMs had an ace up
his sleeve that catapulted him to
Superstar status in my opinion the real
thing that made Dita ROM special is that
he's a systems thinker and that car
we'll do that again Dino ROM stood out
above his peers because of how he
focused on the way design can mold
Society to be more egalitarian and
Humane that's why his products are so
iconic you can feel that Grand Vision
subtly shining through his products for
ROMs it wasn't just about creating a
shelving system or a toaster but it was
about envisioning an entire system
Around The Way We Live I've championed
this mindset in my design work and I
believe it's crucial to the future of
design but ROMs beat me to the punch by
half a century I'm really surprised that
this isn't discussed more often context
changes and ROM's principles don't have
to be our only guide what we should
borrow from ROMs is his faith in
Design's potential to shape a brighter
future like I said earlier I made a
similar video on this topic that was
taken down one person left an incredibly
insightful comment and I'm so glad that
I saved it before it vanished into the
digital ether forever it wraps up ROM's
principles beautifully while adapting
them for our changing World good design
bows to the fundamental principles of
life it's never just about out the
product it's about the all-encompassing
system it must respect all people the
designers Engineers Factory workers end
users and of course the most important
user Mother Earth
damn that's good that is a great
principle to live by big shout out to
Liz Engel for this comment if you want
to support this channel consider joining
me on patreon you'll get access to all
sorts of cool things like working files
for some of my personal projects rough
drafts of scripts that have a lot of
additional information and a whole bunch
of other stuff it also allows me to
focus on topics that you and I want to
talk about rather than whatever we'll
just get the most views thanks for
watching everyone I hope you learned
something and have a great day